[Music]
the following is a production of Frankie
Freitas and the internet Museum of
hologography
[Music]
hello everyone this is Frankie Freitas
and welcome to another week of holotalk
for the week of April 12
1999 I'm getting a little bit of a late
start tonight it's almost midnight
I took a little bit of time today to
update the archive page with more past
Hall talk broadcasts so if you're
interested in hearing some of the past
shows that you may have missed over the
last few weeks I think it may go back
into February if you scroll down the
hollow talk page you will see a link for
past Hollow talk shows and if you click
on that link it will take you to the
archive page now I've got shows archived
going all the way back
to 1997 but I've recently tonight
updated that entire page with shows
going back to February which weren't
archived on a weekly basis but they're
up there now so if you missed any shows
since February you can go back to the
past hole talk page and catch up on
what's been happening this week as I
mentioned last week when we had the
guests down Roadie I wanted to take a
little bit of time
to talk about the test that I did here
with the 15 milliwatt laser diode and
this test worked out really well and I'm
unfortunately I have not had a chance to
shoot another hologram this week with it
in fact I wanted to do an 8x10 I have
one 8 by 10 plate left
but I'm going to hold off with that
because next week I believe on the 15th
or 16th is the delivery date on this I'm
getting a 35 milliwatt diode coming in
and if that proves to be successful
shooting a small four by five inch
hologram then I may use the 35 milliwatt
to shoot the eight by ten
but in any case I want to just give a
little quick rundown this week on this
15 milliwatt laser diode now once you
get up into the powers of 15 milliwatt
um with helium neon laser should give
you the capability of doing some very
nice creative work the five milliwatt
helium neon lasers are great for the
classroom they're great to start out
with holography and there's I know
there's a ton of things that you can do
with a five milliwatt my first five
milliwatt that I had I was actually
doing multiple color reflection
Holograms you
triathanolamine on four by five inch
agfa plates back in the early 80s so
there's a lot of things you can do with
a 4x5 the 15 when you get up into the
tens and 15s especially the 15s I guess
the most famous 15 milliwatt helium neon
laser out there is the spectrophysics
stabilite
124b which I also had in the mid 80s and
I believe I'm not absolutely certain but
I believe I may have paid like four
thousand nine hundred dollars
for that stabilite when it was new from
spectrophysics with the tube The Head
and the power supply I'll have to go
back and see if I can dig out that um
sales receipt for that because I think
that goes back I think I got mine back
in 84 or 85 but there were a lot of very
well-known holographic artists that were
working around the 10 12 15 milliwatt
range for many years and created
beautiful beautiful display
artistic Holograms using 15 milliwatts
of power
so it's it's very advantageous to us to
be able to move up into these higher
Powers now I know some of the Holograms
that are done for conventions the large
Holograms that you see out there are
using 50 milliwatts so it's going to be
interesting to see what this 35
milliwatt does and this is really going
to get us into the ballpark range of
doing some very uh
a large-scale work
I want to run down the prices for this
now the 15 milliwatt laser diode that I
have is putting out 635 nanometers so
we're very close to the 633 line of
helium neon laser
I don't think it's absolutely necessary
to work with 635 everyone when we were
talking very early on about laser diodes
saying it'll be great to get down around
633 nanometers or as close to it as we
can with these laser diodes but the
holographic emulsions are sensitive to a
number of different wavelengths for
instance the BB plates from Germany and
maybe also the slavage materials as well
both have a spike in the response curve
at 647 nanometers for Krypton
so whether you're working with a 635
nanometer diode or 650
uh 635 is going to put you two
nanometers away from 633 650 is going to
put you three nanometers away from 647
so you're in the ballpark for both of
those the main difference the main
difference is what you're going to pay
for the diode now this 15 millilites 635
nanometer diode was
550 dollars assembled now the same
amount of power you're going to be able
to do the same size Holograms you're
going to get the same type of response
for a 650 nanometer diode let me run
down some of these prices for you just
to because I know someone's going to
hear 550 dollars and they're going to
think well that's just putting this
right back where we were before where
people couldn't afford the higher
powered on 550 is a big chunk for some
people especially if you're doing this
as an amateur or hobbyist that's a big
chunk so let's take a look at this now
say for instance that you want to put
your own laser diode module together
here's what it's going to break down to
for 15 milliwatts of power at 650
nanometers
you're going to pay and these are
approximate prices maybe a little bit
more a little bit less but we're only
looking at a few dollars we're not
looking at hundreds uh maybe three
dollars five dollars because they're all
relatively the same price around
you're going to pay ninety dollars for
the 650 nanometer diode that's the raw
diode in the little brass housing these
are tiny little things you have to be
very careful working with them always
make sure you're grounded the slightest
touch of static on a raw diode will
absolutely fry it don't even think about
five one five volts or anything like
that you just just you walking across
the carpet and picking it up you're
going to fry it
so you have to be very careful if you're
doing this I just wanted to put that in
there
ninety dollars for the actual diode now
on top of that
you're going to need a driver
diode's going to have to be it's either
sodded to the driver or some of the
dryer drivers have little uh
receptacles or what we call females that
you can plug the male end of the diodes
into right on the chip itself so that's
going to run you 30. you're going to pay
nine dollars for a collimating lens to
go into the housing excuse me
and twenty dollars for the actual
housing itself now add that up you've
got 90 30 9 and 20 and you're going to
pay
149 for a 15 milliwatt 650 nanometer
diode
now if you'd like to move up to 20
milliwatts
at 650 nanometers you can put one
together Yourself by adding about sixty
five dollars onto the ninety dollars I
think it's 155 dollars for the actual
diode so you're looking at two hundred
and fourteen dollars for 20 milliwatts
at 650. that's that's a nice piece too
now you can also get these assembled if
you've got a little bit more cash to
spend and I'm not selling these I'm just
trying to give people an idea of uh of
what we can do and at what price because
i'm comparing this to the 550 dollars
that was paid for the 635 nanometer 15
milliwatt so you're comparing 149 to 550
and you're still getting the same amount
of power and your Emulsion is still
going to be just as responsive because
it has that Spike right there at 647
nanometers for Krypton
now if you want these already assembled
you're looking at uh let's see I have it
all written down here I'm shooting this
from the hip because like I said it's
almost midnight and I don't want to go
over too long with this but uh
assembled you're looking at 185 dollars
for the 15 milliwatt 650 and you're
looking at 245 dollars for the 20 ml
watt that means that diode module is
going to come already assembled in the
housing the brass housing is going to
have the collimating lens it's going to
have the laser diode it's going to have
two pigtail wires coming out of it we
just hook a couple batteries up to it
and run it
um I did not have any luck running it
off of the power general power supply
now I had someone send me an email
saying that you know but I think they
misunderstood the web page that I put up
meaning that I was running off of one of
those drivers that you just plug into
the wall now this is a very high quality
regulated switching DC power supply from
Power General and I did not get one
image running that diode
module off of that power supply and I
was just just um
doing everything is normal we think
possibly that the AC current going into
these uh into these power has to be very
very clean so we're going to put a scope
on the AC power here in the studio and
find out if there's a lot of noise in
there you can't have a lot of noise
so it looks like the batteries are the
best bet and I also picked something up
that I'm experimenting with do this at
your risk anytime we're working with
this power stuff but at Radio Shack
there's something on sale right now
until May 1st and it's called a portable
CD power pack now it's running at half
price for 19.99 and it provides up to 20
hours run time for CDs that use two AAA
batteries you can charge this up to 500
times so I've been using it and it looks
pretty good it'll put out I think I
measured it at
4.18 volts when it was fully charged and
I just ran it until the diode actually
just one out
but you can charge it up to 500 times so
this may save you a lot of money on
batteries as well
and the number for that is
23-505 that's stock number
23-505 portable CD power pack
but uh
it's actually a little lead acid battery
and it's the size of a CD case that's
how that's the size is very thin if
you've got a CD case sitting there take
a look at it this bad this battery seed
exact same size
and I've been running the infiniter 200
off of that and with very good results
so far
so there you have it folks there's a
little bit of an update on the 15
milliwatt if you'd like to move up in
power a little bit and you've been
working with a five milliwatt laser
pointer
you can see that it's um I don't want to
say inexpensive because that's a
relative word for most people I don't
want to assume that they're sitting here
saying 149 dollars is inexpensive for
some people because I know raising raise
a family myself with three kids who are
now grown but I can remember the day
when the 549 it was going to go for
sneakers it wasn't going to go for a
laser diode so uh
that is relative to you but it's very
inexpensive
considering what you would have paid for
a 15 milliwatt uh healing laser and also
what you would pay for even used
15 milliwatt heat laser it's a great
opportunity to move up and like I had
mentioned next week I will be getting
into 35 milliwatt diode and I'm very
very excited to get in the the ab and
start working with that as you can
imagine and from there who knows where
it's going to go but we're going to
continue building this and see where we
can take it and take it one step at a
time and
small power increments and work with it
and see how it looks and who knows we
could really be into some really
interesting stuff here so I want to
thank you for tuning in and we'll get
back to more guests I'm going to go in
and check the list of guests that I have
scheduled for the rest of the season
send a couple emails out and get a few
uh a few new guests on the show and
don't forget if you'd like to check out
the holotalk past broadcast just scroll
down the whole talk page and click on
that link and it will take you to an
archive of previous broadcasts going all
the way back to
1997 so thank you very much for tuning
in this week and every week I hope you
continue to come back for news and
information and guests
concerning the fields of lasers and
holography right here on the internet
with holotalk the internet's laser and
holography talk show this is Frankie
Freitas thank you for tuning in and I'll
see you next week
would you like to make your own
one-of-a-kind hologram and learn how you
can start making holograms on your own
at the same time you can do this and
much more by attending one of Frankie's
greatest holography workshops from
beginner to Advanced Frank's got a
workshop that's just right for you from
single afternoon evening or weekend
introductory workshops to Wednesday
evening five-week complete courses and
don't forget his newest Workshop laser
pointer holography located just off the
Northeast Extension of the Pennsylvania
Turnpike and Interstate 78 the studio is
a quick non-stop drive from the New York
Philadelphia and Baltimore Washington DC
areas for more information call the
Studio's toll-free hotline at
1-800-458-3525 and begin your own
Journey with holography today that's
1-800-458-3525 for more information on
attending Frankie Freitas holography
Workshop today
foreign